[Music]
so this is a third podcast and yeah so
the last one we offered a constructive
critique of John Peterson
and in this one we're going to go
through some of the comments the
feedback underneath the video and and
else we're trying give a bit more
context and respond to what some are
really sort of valid comments criticisms
and ultimately like so we put out a
video and I wrote a really long novel on
medium which will link to under this as
well
and what was interesting is sort of
developing as Peterson says I write to
know what I think and I really felt like
by writing it I was sort of getting to
know more of what actually thought about
it and then reading people's responses
helping that kind of conversation as
well so there's this these two images to
Peter someone on that on one side is
like Peterson's a cult and it's his
followers are just kind of idle
worshiping and it's and the other side
of which I think more true that
Peterson's actually become a filter for
three thinkers because you have to you
have to have some sense of I'm not going
to listen to what they think I should
think about this guy to be interested in
it you have to go through the pain of
kind of my friends might judge me
because I'm into this guy and come out
the other side and what was amazing in
the responses in the comments was it
really felt like he is this filter for
freethinkers
the the vast majority of them were
offering constructive criticism all of
us and constructive criticism of him and
it felt like a very healthy conversation
yeah yeah and I think I shared that kind
of nervousness maybe from me from from a
different angle which was the you know
Peterson has had so much ad hominem
attack from the media and also just
outright lies as well there's been a lot
of that so there's a nuance to critique
tactics which i think was was kind of
the bulk of our podcast critiquing an
individual which is really what the the
media has done and which for me has no
place in rebel wisdom is its you know
the third thing is critiquing ideas you
know and those things you know
critiquing tactics in particular I think
is a really important thing but also
critiquing the delivery of those ideas
yeah that's that's a good point
yeah which which for me links into
tactics as well I think that what we're
doing is offering it in the spirit of
Peterson himself what is not required is
unconditional positive regard what is
required is genuinely wanting success
and wanting the best of him and the best
of this to succeed and I hope that we
are coming from that place I mean only
other I mean people would do make their
own judgments but I genuinely believe
I've wrestled with this stuff we've
wrestled with this stuff and we're
trying to come from that place and so I
just yeah it's one a recap just in case
people are watching this without having
watched the first podcast we basically
said three things that the message could
be framed in a way that would reach
people that are resistant to at the
moment that they're maybe he could look
at retreating from some of the sort of
daily combat the media firefighting
stuff kind of he's off he's talked
before about you shouldn't put pearls
before swine and maybe it's getting to
that stage and also that I am not seeing
the same JP as I did a while ago and it
would be almost impossible for him to be
the same because of the unfair attacks
that he's had but why the Kathy Newman
interview worked was that he it wasn't
just he had the facts and he out did her
on that level there was a humor and a
wit and a performance to that that won
people over and I actually messaged him
after that he was still he wasn't famous
he is now so culprit ply at that point
just to say wow fantastically well done
on that interview I know that that will
reach people who were resistant already
and I don't see so much of that
anymore so that was kind of the other
part of it yeah and just at that point
after the Kathy Newman interview he
mentioned you know he talked about
animus possession and he talked about if
you engage in the argument with you know
with the energy Kathy Newman was coming
from you've already lost the argument
and in a sense I think the more he's
delved into the mainstream media and the
more they've started to kind of direct
the conversation the more and more it's
been more difficult not to engage in
that argument you know so I think that's
that's part of the kind of expanding out
of the reason for those tactics being
important I think yeah and one more
point that actually came out in the
writing of the article and in some of
the feedback is is there a deeper
theological point or resolution than
what Peterson's putting out there and
I'm gonna unpack and explore that with
Louise Mazzanti who appeared in the
glitch in the matrix film hello so we
thought it would be interesting to kind
of delve into the comment and then pick
out different critiques or ideas or
things people were adding so the first
one wanted to talk about is in a couple
of the comments this idea of what I call
like the Fairweather friends argument of
you know this is this isn't the time to
be criticizing Peterson you know he
needs support right now you know you
shouldn't be doing that so so what's
your take on that I think this goes to
the heart of what we were saying really
the idea that polarization encourages
this son of a some men mentality and
ultimately I think what Peterson is is
saying is trying to get us the other
side of this and this is something I
reckon Brett Weinstein talked about in
the Dave Rubin podcast which is
incredible if anyone's not seeing it go
and watch it
amazing amazing podcast they said that
in the past speaking out against being
ejected from your tribe would have been
a fatal thing throughout most of human
history so we we have this as a kind of
internalized biological reality that
this kind of feminist is tribalism which
I would argue is why with
like me to wipe ourselves out if we
don't evolve to the past this kind of
reactivity is social media makes it
worse everything makes it worse and at
the moment this kind of polarization or
this kind of dynamic is is seem to be at
its peak and Pedersen is the one man
kind of lightning rod for this new
culture wars I think to add to that as
well that there's there's an interesting
concept of you know a tribe of
individuals very different from from a
different kind of tribe and I think a
big part of Peterson's message is in the
primacy of the individual of your own
experience and your own truth I'm
speaking the truth certainly if I was
going to pick a side I know its side I
pick but I'm trying to kind of see that
is there a chance that we can get past
this whole game of picking sides
we might be naive we might be wrong and
I certainly felt in myself as we put the
stuff out there this sort of sense of
nervousness and sense of kind of is this
right am i betraying something fighting
with this other sense of no this is my
truth this is what I have to add to the
conversation and I have to and I have to
add this like Peterson talks about it's
like things go corrupt when people don't
speak their truth and I might be wrong I
mean this is an ongoing conversation
it's ongoing
I mean that's another thing that he says
it's like what the do you know I
mean you're an idiot you know you don't
know enough by definition I don't know
enough by definition we don't know
enough by definition we're all kind of
groping towards the truth as best we can
and this is what we're trying to do and
I believe that we're also like we're
teaching men's work as well and this is
a core part of what we're teaching like
speaking your truth giving your
brother's honest reflections and being
really reflective of what is coming up
in myself at the same time whether I'm
just projecting my own kind of sense of
superiority or whatever out onto the
world and try it we're in the process of
trying to do that at the same time and I
think the key word is it's a process it
is a process of like you've said you
know you speak to know you speak to
think
and it's a process in the men's work as
well of especially that people often
find it difficult to reflect to to you
know another guy in the group of the
things of hey hip man here's where I see
your blind spots and you know in the
groups we go around and we'll kind of
listen in and the circles and be like
and if someone is kind of falling in to
pleasing of like oh yeah you can
sometimes be a little bit mean but
you're really great otherwise you know
it's like you you know one of the things
office say is you're not serving you're
not helping him you're not helping him
by pleasing the help will be reflection
because we cannot see our own blind
spots by definition so that's why the
college that yeah so to move on to
another question a kind of a couple of
comments around the theme of you guys
have lost your nerve have you lost your
nerve David it would have been much
easier for us to carry on and we are
going to carry on doing sort of Peterson
themed interviews and work because I
think the the perspective that he's
bringing is the most complete thing I've
ever seen and so we are going to use it
as a window into other thinkers and the
window into in terms of broadening
broadening out as much as we can and it
it would have been much easier not to do
this so have we lost our nerve I don't
think so
one or two comments around yeah you
piggybacked you know with piggybacked on
Peterson and then now we're stabbing him
in the back by critiquing him what are
your thoughts on that and also there was
one guy who said and that's not what men
do men back each other up it's like I
have I was genuinely concerned that he
might think that as well like I actually
sent him a message
about that a while ago saying look I I'm
really trying to act ethically we the
interview gave us really did give us a
boost and allow us to kind of attract
attention with rebel wisdom and you are
he also uploaded the glitch in the
matrix to his channel which gave us
another boost as well and I'm eternally
grateful for that all I can do is
explain where I'm coming from and how
it's got to this point and people can
make their own judgments as to whether
that's
piggybacking on his success or not I
used to be a journalist well I am that I
am a journalist documentary maker
reporter I work for channel 4 news for
many years I made documentaries I found
Peterson July no June of last year and I
immediately became hooked and I wrote
the medium article truth in the time of
chaos one of the first medium articles I
think about him where I transcribed a
load of his stuff and put up no 3,000
words something like that and it was
because of that that I then got the
interview with him when I was going to
the leaf of going over to one of the
Bible lectures and then thought well I'm
a journalist I might save and get
interview with him sent him that the
article and he really liked it said he
done it's a very careful job and he was
happy to do an interview which I'm again
very grateful for and then after doing
the interview I then thought well from
the beginning I've been thinking there's
a lot of people who are just not seeing
this message they're getting hung up on
the political stuff they're not seeing
what he's actually about and so I
thought okay I'm gonna make a
documentary and so I made truth in the
time of chaos to try and provide that
kind of context to explain what he was
really about like the theological stuff
in the interview I did with him we
didn't talk about the trans stuff or the
pollak politic stuff at all the least
interesting thing about him in my view
is the politic stuff the most
interesting thing is the deep the deep
mythological the deep archetype or the
de Young in integration which he's
bringing forward and so a lot of what we
talked about was about synchronicity and
about young and it was about this kind
of deeper message and so I put that
article that documentary out and then
the Kathy Newman interview happened and
I was kind of trying to leave behind the
scenes between him and Kathy for a while
and because that's what I thought it was
amazing synchronicity we we talked about
synchronicity that was basically the
topic of our conversation and
synchronicity being like amazing
coincidences that tell you something
meaningful like there's some there's
some how mentor
and then he comes to the UK I'm the only
person who's done a documentary about
him he then leads to fame on the show I
used to work on with Kathy Newman who is
an ex colleague of mine and I I message
them both immediately after the
interview independently to say to
Peterson as I just said well that well
done that was amazing I think the humor
and the wit that's probably one people
over and to Kathy to say I really liked
that the way that you you guys warm to
each other by the end because there was
a kind of genuine kind of kind of
respect by the end and they both
responded and and then this whole thing
blew up and I really felt I was like wow
this is an amazing position and I really
wanted to kind of Liege between them for
a while that's what I thought I was
meant to do it's like what's the meaning
of the synchronicity where you're meant
to kind of try and help them renegotiate
because on one side Peterson was very
upset on one side I know for sure that
they were it wasn't spin like Kathy did
feel under attack Channel 4 News did
feel under attack it wasn't spin I do
have my doubts about that then calling
in security experts or or the fact that
they put that out I think I mean they're
journalists they know how to may know
how to control the narrative I do have
my suspicions around them doing that
which I didn't at the time but I
developed them afterwards but Peterson
was very angry about the fact that it
was now being spun as Kathy was a victim
and all their stuff and I completely
understood his perspective as well and I
agree with it but I also knew that from
inside channel 4 news that's not what
they were thinking they were genuinely
were upset at the comments that Kathy
was getting and I know that privately
they were getting some really horrific
stuff so it wasn't I could see both
sides and I was trying kind of the ACE
and Peterson was interested in in having
a second interview and wanted to do to
do it
Channel 4 News just wanted it to go away
so eventually I was like a case of what
am I meant to do with this I and I
realized okay I'll put out glitch in the
matrix or just all of these ideas that
have been sort of bubbling away about
since the Trump election I then
downloaded in
you glitching the matrix put it together
in about two weeks and I was in the
Channel 4 News newsroom two weeks before
I put that documentary out freelancing
there my freelance there since I left I
knew I would not be able to go back into
that newsroom when I put that
documentary out just they were critic
criticisms of Channel 4 News in there I
was pretty much weighing into the debate
around Kathy Newman where they just
wanted to protect her at that time
understandably because some of the some
of the abuse she was getting was really
serious and I knew it makes things
incredibly difficult so but I made that
decision at that point that I would that
that wasn't my path anymore that
actually this creating rebel wisdom
outside the mainstream media has been
the thing that I've decided to do so I
was kind of I was accepting the
possibility that I was ending my career
in news and current affairs by doing
putting that out I was being disloyal to
them so people can judge as to whether
that's a sacrifice or not and I think
Peterson's probably made bigger
sacrifices but I think I have taken
decisions that I think I do have skin in
this game so what you're saying is we
live in the matrix what I'm saying is
yes watch glitch in the matrix another
interesting question is is you know
people were asking well are we saying
that Peterson should censor himself or
should he you know should he change his
tone what do you thoughts on that I
don't think he should stop speaking the
truth I think he should just do it
smarter I think that and this is
something that Andrew Sweeney who wrote
a blog post alongside it talked about
that this idea of the castration cult
the sort of great mother and what was
seeing if you'd kind of look at it from
the archetypal perspective the media is
acting like a castration cult Peterson
needs to behave and he's to stop being
angry he needs to do this it's like this
kind of lecturing finger wagging kind of
anti masculine tone to a lot of a lot of
it which and we're not saying Peterson
needs to behave and buts
what I am saying is that I think he
could frame it in a way that would that
would reach more people and that I think
he is because at first I was thinking
well he's just speaking the truth and
just allowing it to fall as it will it's
fine if the media misrepresents him he's
not playing the media game which I had
some sympathy for but I don't think
that's true I think he is playing the
media game in some ways like think about
Milo he's never been on Milo's show I I
assume that Milo would want him in a
heartbeat he's made a decision not to go
on Milo show I'm assuming I might be
wrong I'm just speculating here but he's
gone on just about everyone else's so
he's made a decision to keep a distance
from Milo I think he's right to keep a
distance from Lyle I think Milo is now
damaged goods and Milo is kind of a
textbook example of what can happen
Milo's a provocateur peterson on a
provocateur he's provocate he's
provoking a response but he's not doing
it deliberately Milo was doing it
deliberately so there was a kind of he
was playing with fire and the danger
with petersen like mine I was still
doing okay got his own podcast he's
probably never going to want four people
to provide him money he still got a
fanbase but he is at in terms of his
influence on the national conversation
or the international conversation it's
zero he is now he has been defined and
discarded by the national conversation
Peterson is too important for that to
happen to and I think he is a different
character than Milo and I think he has
different motivations with Milo as it
was a case of this was kind of bound to
happen he was a shooting star that was
bound to flame out I'm not convinced
that the Peterson is bound to flame out
or should flame out I think he's
bringing something that's still gonna be
relevant to the like two hundred years
time whereas I don't think Milo is and
one of the reasons they dropped his book
is it was complete if you read the
reports he's he was saying he was made a
career up saying things that no one else
would say but apart from that he he's
not it's not an intellect
it's not on the same level of someone
like Peterson yeah that brings me to
another point that kind of came up in
the comments as well which is slightly
link to it this idea of you know you
well you can't talk to the radical left
there's no talking to them there's no
point in trying to win them over you
know etc the way I see the link to that
is that the media the mainstream media
is kind of the act a big access point to
the kind of really radical sjw's my
thinking on that is that I think there's
truth in that I think the most radical
extreme they're not reachable by
Peterson's message there you know but I
don't think they're the majority by any
means in fact the the audience that
dimension media allows you to talk to is
the massive group of fairly reasonable
open-minded people on the Left who
really could use Peterson's message who
need to be read pilled effectively and
that that makes it matter the tactics
you use to reach them because they are
they are being kind of shamed into
having a certain worldview which is
based around shame that kind of social
justice worldview and that's a strong
pull on them of like you're not allowed
to listen to this person because it's
they have a deep concern with how you
think what you believe and they can take
things like hit pieces and make it a
very effective tool to keep people there
so yeah there's two things here one
Peterson says that sanity is out sourced
like sanity is such a complicated
problem that we outsource it to other
people in some ways we we we moderate
our behavior by the reaction that we
have from other people so sense making
is also out sourced we we we all to some
degree either we make up our own minds
or we follow others but we can't make up
our own minds all the time like we all
have these we take cues from what other
people like or from from people that we
see on Twitter it's impossible to make
up our own minds entirely about every
single thing all the time we're always
influenced by what other people are
thinking and and some kind of peer
not peer pressure but but peer like our
anchor points so and my worry is that
Peterson has lost a lot of key anchor
points who are not interested in sort of
delving in deeper into his message I on
my Twitter feed I try and have a balance
I try and balance it with different
perspectives and I see a lot of
reasonable intelligent left-leaning
journalists who I consider open-minded
and reachable sharing sort of Peterson
hit pieces and saying well I always knew
there was something about this guy and
now I realize so I feel like he's losing
that Center so another thing that's come
up in the comments is that what is most
striking about the podcast is that all
the advice we were giving Peterson
applies much much more to the regressive
left the kind of social justice mindset
by a factor of like a million what are
your thoughts yes it's true absolutely
true it does doesn't mean that that 2%
or 5% is irrelevant and I've written
extensively about kind of less
reactivity and we will talk a lot more
about that but it doesn't mean that
there is nothing to learn on the other
side and I've kind of reflect on Jocko
Willick Peterson's been on jaha willing
to podcast he talks about extreme
ownership the buck stops with me he
talks about when things went wrong up on
a tour in Iraq
and he just said it's my fault good if
you say it's my fault whatever reaction
you're getting whatever people are
misunderstanding if you say it's my
fault
suddenly you're you then have some
ownership of it if you just keep saying
no it's just then it's just then they're
doing this they're doing this then
that's a very weak position to be in
because you can't do anything about it
if you accept that you can do anything
about anything then you're empowering
yourself there's this other sense of if
you're in an argument with someone you
and you can't seem to get through it and
you can tell they're being completely
unreasonable the only way out of that
argument either you kind of fight or you
don't see that person anymore if you
want to get through that argue
and says a family member and you have no
choice but to get through that argument
if you are seeing more of the dynamics
than the person who's reacting to you
you're the only one that can shift that
dynamic actually is that unfair if
they're being unreasonable yes it's
completely unfair tough life is unfair
but you the only person who can shift
the dynamics is the person who's seen
the bigger picture and I think Peterson
has the capacity to see a bigger picture
that the media just doesn't have and I
do think there are there are ways of
framing that will at least kind of talk
to the middle if not yeah the extremes
are kind of unreachable I think that
Peterson he's channeling like this this
old spirit of the divine masculine and
it is absolutely essential we cannot do
without it and he is channeling this
thing into the culture in a big way and
his successes shows how much we're
thirsting for it this this important
masculine energy but it needs to be
matched by a feminine energy of equal
power and weight because and I think
this is this is why I think there is
some truth in like the New York Times
article that called him custodian of the
patriarchy I think on some level I do
think he may and may be quite rightly is
concerned about what's happened since
the 60s like we have started sharing
space between men and women is that
gonna work out or is there not going to
work out we don't know it's clearly
creating huge difficulties and I think
he's genuinely not sure whether it's a
good idea or a bad idea I think people
are picking up on that and criticizing
him for it but ultimately we're not
going to wind the clock back we are
going to have to go through and forward
and find this synthesis which is going
to be as Jordan Greenhalgh talks about
what we have and he also frames it by
saying these are very difficult
conversations to have these are hugely
important but very difficult
conversations to have we have the
feminine rising into power power and we
also need the feminine to rise into
responsibility at the same time and
those two things need
happen need to happen at the same time
and it's it's certainly true that women
now have power to destroy men destroy
men's reputations destroy men's careers
and that power and it's it's right that
some people do have their careers
destroyed and some people do have the
reputations ruined that's right we're
not going back to the 1950s sort of
madmen culture but also that with great
power comes great responsibility I think
for me what woke me up as a woman about
Jordan Peterson was that he was
beginning to talk about a longing in
culture and longing we are in this time
of cares and where are the axioms where
are the things that are true at a deeper
levels and you know as women we already
know that there are these truths we've
just been really really trained to not
feel it and not speak it and he speaks
to her but and I really like the way
that he's saying hello man where are you
where is a divine masculine because the
divine feminine has has come massively
into the world none of the divine
feminine but you know that with a lot of
shadow as well Carly exactly chopping
off and saying enough yeah but it's run
amok and we need the divine masculine we
need to strong the deep the mature
masculine to stand up and say I'm here
and we need we need the feminine to do
the same and that's what I feel is is
what Peterson is is pointing yet but
missing out and he's speaking more he's
speaking more to men he's speaking more
to the masculine I don't feel that he's
saying the feminine is not important at
all but he's creating a space and I want
women to stand up and say okay what is
this space from a woman's perspective
how can we fill this space but this and
this also you were just saying the
Divine Feminine is showing up a lot of
Carly at the moment brilliant kind of
archetypal framework and it's like and
it's absolutely right that she does
because men need to find their their
grounding men need to find their balls
men need to find to stay
masculinity and say enough women test
men to see how grounded they are that
happens automatically it needs to happen
women evolutionarily that has to happen
women have to test men like you women
had a far bigger investment in
childbirth and bringing up children and
so women constantly test men they it's
an evolutionary necessity and it's
actually something that's very valuable
to men too for that to happen it's like
that's how we evolved is is through that
kind of being tested and standing in our
truth and standing in our masculinity
and women are very there's a kind of
idea of men or concept
men test ideas and women test men now
it's very easy to misunderstand that and
say well do you mean women don't have
ideas that's outrageous did it is no but
that has always been the truth women
have a much more direct kind of sense of
when someone's really aligned when
someone's really grounded so men may
test ideas but they may not be connected
to any sort of deeper emotional truth
and they can go off on all sorts of
directions women in the past have been
really good at kind of seeing where the
alignment is and I think men are
developing more emotional intelligence
are more able to do that than before but
I still think women have a deeper lived
biological reality of really really
seeing that deeper alignment and that's
why the me to discussion again that's
why it's really interesting because it
shows these dynamics because what's been
happening right now is that women have
really really gone from him and really
really testing and said speaking up
challenging and what's happened is that
men have kind of retreated to the corner
gotten defensive or have really lost the
masculinity given away their balls and
what we're not seeing is that men are
stepping up and saying okay enough but
from a grounded perspective from a
perspective of hearing and embracing the
pain
but also saying there's there's a limit
because the feminine needs that that
it's it's no fun if we keep running and
running and and and nailing men per se
on everything like creating a society
where where where men are dangerous for
women and this is what you know that's
that's a danger for what's happening if
we don't have a much more balanced
conversation about this because as women
we don't want all the power we want we
want to share that space and and it
seems like we both forgotten that we so
we're so engaged in the antagonism in
clearing the space that we forget why
we're clearing it what one I'm gonna
come back to what do we want to fill
that space with what is the synthesis
look like what does the what would a
healthy relationship look like I love
this question because this is the most
open question we can have right now I
don't have the answer this is what we're
developing together right now this is
why I want to say to my my sister's all
the women are there come on let's do
that let's find out what is it to be a
woman because we've forgotten with Luke
we've totally caught off from from those
roots and let the men figure out what is
it about to be a man and let's come
together and see what happens in that
space if we are all the same in
post-modernism nothing is happening this
is why we see our society isn't isn't a
complete crisis this is only gonna get
worse because we don't have we don't
have a solution right now and this is
why we need a co-creation a synthesis to
go to the next level we can't go to the
next level on our own the resources the
the physical resources of the planet the
mental resources our of our thinking
they are exhausted they are not creating
that next level that we need to go to
and this is why for me this whole
discussion between men and women between
the feminine and the masculine these
archetypes they are so essential because
they are leading us to the next point of
evolution so I don't have the answer
what is that but I want to say let
find out
you